Okay,
this is a transcript for a case study we're going to write,
and this case study is about financial
modeling. For a startup or SMB,
uh, specifically making an operational financial
model, uhm,
and I really want this case study slash blog.
article to get across the point that,
uhm,
a financial model is an operational tool that
should be prioritized ahead of the business.
Uhm,
developing out your product to a go-to-market level.
And what I see as a mistake,
you know, almost, heh, 100% of the time,
no. With,
I would say, like, 90 plus percent of companies,
founders, directors, management people that I talk to have
a Thank you. misconception about what a financial model
does for the organization.
I think the misconception is that it's
for accounting and it's for raising funds and that you have to have a
really good idea about how to make the model correct before
you spend too much time on the model. And,
uhm, what I want to get across in this paper is
the correctness of the financial model is not that important.
It's the exercise of creating the model which,
uhm, tends to flesh out all the
details of your business as well as show what other I call golden paths,
uhm, where revenue or profit is particularly
high when modeled against the work and
or expenses that go into generating that profit.
And without actually being able doing that math and having it on paper,
uh, it's all just assumptions and most assumptions are wrong.
And so when I talk to startup founders who are usually very
product based, growth based people,
uhm, they're not. They're not prioritizing the creation of even
a straw model, uh, financial model that they look at weekly
to help their decisions. And then when I talk to them as a consultant,
uh,
they are stressed out and have decision paralysis because
they don't have any model that they're looking at.
And the argument I get when I ask them why they don't have a
model or if I offer to help, they said that they say that they're
not ready for one. Because they're not sure what assumptions
to put in there yet and they want to develop out the product more
before that. And this is, I think, a big difference between successful
founders and, uhm,
and unsuccessful ones. And I mean successful in the way that they get funding
or they, or their idea becomes self-sufficient.
I don't mean exit or anything like that. I mean baseline success and viability.
Uhm, and so now let's talk about what
the model looks like when done correctly,
like by Wolfpack. What the purpose,
what it looks like and what the purpose is. Uh,
what it looks like, uh, is,
is at least three-fold. Uhm,
one of the deliverables from the financial model is the three-statement
package. This is profit and loss,
balance sheet, and cash flow.
It's mostly about P&L, but the balance sheet and cash flow just kind of
fall out. But as far as operations go,
you're mostly creating the P&L,
uh, and that's your operational,
uhm, uh,
financial document that you'll be looking at the most.
And even when you're pre-revenue,
uhm,
if you're working on it, there's an,
there's a line on your P&L,
which is headcount, and if you're not paying yourself,
then you're creating shareholder equity,
by putting time into the business,
and by setting up a financial model,
and just simply understanding that,
and, and updating this monthly, with the month end,
you know, close of month, uhm, uhm, month and then close
type of situation, where, you see,
how much time did I put into my business,
and what did that equate to, in shareholder equity,
that's just, a use right there,
which is, a nice, uhm,
punch in the arm,
for, the work you're putting into your business,
that will actually show on the financial document,
and when investors look at this, they will be really impressed with that level
of awareness, and it, it does not take much,
to get this set up, and that it only takes one day,
for month ending close to update the model.
And so, I'm not suggesting that you make this model,
and open it every day, and make it super accurate,
that's the job for your investors. or accountant, uhm,
later when the business is profitable. But,
right now, my suggestion is that you build a
robust model over the course of two to three days,
and then get a lot of assumptions in question.
And then you look at this model one time per week,
anywhere from 30 to 90 minutes max,
and, uh, maybe even,
maybe even one hour max in the once a week look.
That's really just to see, just to keep it loaded in your mind,
and, and see if you have any ideas that haven't gotten on to the,
the financial model notion task list.
And also, when you have wins,
you're going to want to go ahead and go in there into the model
and check things off and,
ah, update timelines, and that's a really exciting process.
The other great purpose for maintaining the financial model is
so when you have conversations with,
development partners, investors,
ah, even friends and family who are,
or mentors who are working on the project,
this model is an amazing source of truth that will be able to give
you, ah, a quick foundation that you can learn from.
Look at the model and load into your mind your full financial trajectory,
and even if you're not going for venture capital,
you're your own venture capitalist then. You know,
you should still operate in, ah, the way that a successful venture
capitalist should as would. You're not going to reinvent the way to fund an
application. Uhm,
you're just, if you don't want a VC, you're your own VC.
So you should still follow the VC's,
ah, kind of best practices in order to make your,
your business successful. One of their best practices is have this three
financial document model maintained and going all the time.
You know, and if that sounds like a lot of work, you don't know
what you're doing yet. Because it should only take two to three days to
create a straw model of a startup or a small to medium-sized business.
Uhm, you know, once you have that set up and you get on a
weekly cadence of 30 to 60 minutes of poking at it,
updating it, thinking about it, And then you can see,
You start to delegate, you have ideas, you talk to your accountants,
say, here's my straw model, you know,
give me feedback, add to it, and I want a month-end close,
you know, which is super important to being a big-boy business.
If you don't have a month-end close, you're not really a business.
In my opinion, as an operator,
you're still very much a startup or even in the idea phase if you
don't understand the, the purpose and the impact
that a month-ending close cadence can have,
uhm, on your development process.
Okay, the other big thing about why a financial model really early
in the process is necessary so you can find the highest return time for
yourself. This, the most scarce thing for,
in a startup, a, a, a, a, solopreneur startup,
is time. And so,
that means that, uhm, uh,
what you need to do is get a value of ROI on
your own hours. You can't do that on your head.
And you, you know, you're going to assume and get it wrong.
And so, the financial model will help you figure out how to estimate that
ROI based on what part of your project you're working on,
uhm, or based on,
uh, which product you're product or sub-product you're
working on. It will also help you estimate,
uhm, ad return.
And so, you can build a simulator inside of your model to,
say, if I add, uhm, add this much ad spend to get this many
followers and then with this percent conversion,
what does that path make me? Those aren't the types of things you should
think about in your head or do on a napkin or in Excel.
Uhm, it should be built into your financial model.
Um, and so, uh,
you know, founders and directors of small companies have to
wear many hats and make many decisions all the time.
To me, uh, the financial model,
uh, helps those decisions get made.
On their own, where,
and what I mean by that is not taking away free will,
but the financial model shows infeasibility with math that you
can't really argue it. And,
you know, I call it infeasibility because I'm a,
I'm a statistics person. If you're more qualitative,
then you just call that a more expensive path,
you know, or a, an extremely expensive path,
right? And as much as you want to make all the businesses' dreams come
true, there's 2,000 workable hours in the year and
you have to pick. To not have a financial model helping
you which ones to pick, from the standpoint of which one's going to sustain
the business financially, then you you're really shooting yourself in the foot.
And since most founders are, are, and solopreneurs are also the product developer,
like, you're sitting there looking at the wall wondering what to do when the
financial model will tell you, this is the only one or two ways you
can go about getting the results that you on this app,
uh, when looking at this audience. And if you have ten other ideas,
then you need to eliminate those ten now and focus on those two.
Uhm, the idea is that those two will not get finished if you're diluting
your attention, focusing on the other ten as well.
Uhm, you're, the only way you're going to know that's happening is through modeling
your, your business and your time and checking in on it once a week.
Uhm,
what I do is track my time,
although I'm in the middle of, uh,
improving my time tracking system.
I think being responsible for your own time tracking is
too distracting. I think,
uh, either an,
an end of day estimate,
you know, uhm, is, is better than disrupting your
front, you know, your work time to be thinking about what you're working on
and thinking about time tracking. It's like, just counterproductive.
So, either utilize an app.
That, uh,
that tracks what projects you're working on, you know,
that's running on your machine and, and tracks that shit.
Or, uhm, I was thinking about developing my own,
but I'm reinventing the wheel and,
and was gonna use it as a team.
Teaching tool, but anyway, that's a tangent. Time tracking is really important so you
can line it up with your model. Uhm,
for example, if you have three features that you're working on for your application,
and one is gonna have a hundred thousand dollar a year return,
and the other two are gonna have, uh,
ten thousand dollar return per year,
the model tells you, make sure you're starting with that one high return
feature, and then you line that up with your time tracking to,
at the end of the week, look and be like, did I work on
the feature that's going to have the highest return the most?
If not, why? What is blocking me from working on the highest return stuff?
If you're not tracking that, you can see how,
you're just guessing. And I've done this,
I've lived that life. I'm on the other side of it,
where make the model, track the time,
get your employees on board with some rough time tracking and show them the
return. And if you're prof,
if you're thinking about profit first,
then what you're gonna, ah, it.
Give back to your employees by saying,
I know you're working on this one thing a lot,
but when it's done, you're all getting this reward,
you know, and have transparency into the rationale going into why we're working
on this particular project now until it's done versus these other projects that you
think are really important, which they are.
They're just going to happen later in this year,
you know. So financial model is a lot about taking time
that feels very granular and taking it like they need to
get done now and spreading them across bigger time periods,
quarters, years,
you know, because in 2028, when you look back in 2026,
you're not going to say, what did I finish in August?
You're going to say, what did I finish in 2026?
The mentality of, uhm,
quarterly goals and annual goals,
even for a startup is really important because that just is
how history reads. You know,
this isn't even really that much of a philosophy. This is really close to
fact. No one in the future says,
tell me what was successful about February 2025.
They say what was successful about 2025.
And so plan your business that way as well with these larger initiatives.
To think about your future measurement of
the quarter or of the year. Does it matter what happens,
you know, does it matter that Project X,
Y, and Z are done by the end of August?
Or does it matter that X, Y, and Z are done by the end
of the year? The model will show you the actual difference.
Uhm, and a well-made model you only need to look
at to, like, answer these questions as they come up.
Uh, maybe you have,
you have an initiative that you could source out to an independent
contractor. Uhm, you would use the model to see what would be the return
on the feature or application that contractor is building,
model out how long it would take, get that down and write it in.
Don't make it a one-off. Incorporate it into the model.
Put it on the calendar. You know,
well, when would I have time to do this? And since you've been maintaining
the model, you would see what goes before it,
uhm, and, and what blocks it.
And by the end of getting it into the model,
you might either rule it out, refine it, uh, get some other feature ahead
or behind, or, uhm, behind it.
So all sorts of things happen in the
exercise of maintaining the model. There could reach beyond
the financial documents that are the output of the model.
Uhm, as a founder you're always thinking about hiring
and independent contractors and,
uhm, board members and things like that.
And, uh, this financial model is just crucial to be a centerpiece to those
discussions. Uhm, you'll shorten meetings a lot by going into it and,
and just all huddling around the model to show what you've already put time
into, uhm, and what,
what assumptions have been made or ruled out.
And then there's less discussion from your,
your board who's not in operations every day.
If they have an idea you've already ruled out,
you can say, hey, let me show you why I've ruled that out,
not have a whole discussion about it.
Uh, when you have the model to show, hey,
board member, that's actually less profitable than you think,
uhm, or, hey, board member, the thing you're telling me not to do is
actually a lot more profitable than you think.
Uhm, you can't just say that. You have to have numbers to do that.
So, don't put it on your phone. Founder plate to have to come up
with all that evidence on the spot. Maintain the model along the way,
and then you'll have that evidence on the fly. Okay,
so that's plenty of, uh,
information on the case study slash blog entry for this why
to have a financial model all the time and its uses.
And so this is the transcript and to create that copy.